Guide to the French Revolution and Napoleonic Period Manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
French Revolution and Napoleonic Period Manuscripts, 1752-1882 (bulk 1788-1815)
- Autograph manuscripts
  - Bes-Cd (Box 2)
    - Caulaincourt, Baron, to Baron Bignon*, 23 March 1819; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 46b)
      ALS in French: Writing from Paris on behalf of Napoleon, whom he still refers to as "l'Empereur," Caulaincourt thanks Baron Bignon for sending him a copy of a work Bignon recently published ("Des proscriptions") containing an homage to Napoleon, and gives him the assurance that Napoleon will get it.
  - Ce-Del (Box 3)
    - General Cervoni, to the Prefet Maritime de Toulon, 23 Jan. 1801; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 1)
      ALS in French, plus a second letter [also 1801], plus translation
    - General Cervoni, to the Minister of Finance, 15 October 1802; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Champagny, Jean Baptiste de, to Senator Lemercier*, 21 March 1806; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 3a)
      ALS in French: about the export to Spain of handkerchiefs made in Vendée ("mouchoirs de Cholet")and Bassses-Pyrénées ("mouchoirs de Béarn").
    - Champagny, Jean Baptiste de*, 19 February 1812; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 3b)
      Two notes in French dictated by Napoleon and related to the special revenues of the State (domaine extraordinaire, "ce que les Américains ont [r]apporté" [cotton supplies], "ventes de denrées coloniales [colonial goods] qui ont eu lieu en Allemagne", "produits des mines d'Idria [quicksilver mines] qui sont à Venise" etc.) needed to fund the French invasion of Russia (June 1812).
    - Champagny, Jean Baptiste de, to ?, n.d. [1823?]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 3c)
    - General Championnet, 1799; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Brevet in French
    - Champagny, Jean Baptiste de, to ?, n.d. [1823?]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Championnet, General Jean-Antoine, 1799; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Champollion-Figeac, Jean-Jacques, to M. Delafontaine, n.d. [1820s]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 5)
      [Bibliothèque du Roi/Ecole royale des chartes] ALS in French
    - Chaptal, Antoine, to Gaudin*, 28 december 1801; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 6a)
      ALS in French: a plan to halting the illicit commerce of grain was approved
    - Chaptal, Antoine {Minister of the Interior], to the Minister of War, 25 Oct. 1802; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 6b)
    - Chaptal, Antoine {Minister of the Interior], to M. de Salver (?), 25 Oct. 1802; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 6c)
      ALS in French re: a payment by the Banque de France
    - Charbonnel, Comte Joseph, to Marshall Ney, January 1811; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Charlet, Nicolas Toussaint, to ?, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Chasset, to the Minister of Finance, 23 Nov. 1802; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 9a)
    - Chateaubriand, vicomte de, to "Madame la comtesse [del Drago?]"*, 14 December 1826; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 9b)
    - Chaumette, Procureur de la Commune, 6 May 1793; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Chaumette, Procureur de la Commune, 2 Oct. 1793; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Chemineau, Colonel, 1811; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - General Clarke, Directeur du cabinet historique et topographique militaire du Directoire, 1796; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 13a)
    - General Clarke, to the "Commission des Petitions", 14 March 1808; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 13b)
    - Henri Jacques Guillaume Clarke, Duc de Feltre, 1810-1815; 3 leaves (Box 3, Folder 14a)
    - Henri Jacques Guillaume Clarke, Duc de Feltre, to vice-amiral comte Decrès*, 6 September 1813; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 14b)
      ALS in French about the geopolitical situation in Europe: "L'Impératrice est arrivée hier [à la Malmaison] à deux heures du matin, fatiguée à ce qu'on m'a dit. Les sentiments qu'elle a fait voir depuis cette guerre avec son Père ont été tels que l'Empereur doit être content. Je ne puis comprendre que l'Autriche, qui désirait l'alliance avec la France à l'époque déjà ancienne du traité de Campo-Formio, puisse s'en départir en ce moment où il doit lui être facile de s'entendre avec nous. On loue ici la modération de l'Empereur avec son beau-père et ses égards délicats envers son épouse... J'aurais bien désiré pouvoir donner à l'Empereur de bonnes nouvelles de l'Espagne..."
    - Henri Jacques Guillaume Clarke, Duc de Feltre*, 12 Dec. 1816; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 14c)
      ALS in French: promotion of Jacques Guilhaumond to the rank of lieutenant
    - Henri Jacques Guillaume Clarke, Duc de Feltre*, 23 January 1839; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 14d)
      "Etat des services [official record of the military service] du Maréchal Duc de Feltre, 1765-1818" [Printed]
    - Clauzel, Bertrand, comte, April and August 1817; 4 leaves (Box 3, Folder 14e)
      2 ALS in French to William Lee, with typewritten English translations added
    - Clavière, Etienne, aux Directeurs des Postes, 1793; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Cochon [de Lapparent], Charles, to Merean [or Mereau], 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Cochon [de Lapparent], Charles, to Merle d'Aubigné, 1797; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Colbert(-Chabanais), General Edouard de, to Clarke, 16 Febr. 1812; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Colli, General, to "his friend Luciano", 2 Nov. 1801; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Collin de Sussy, Jean-Baptiste, to "the Directeur général des Douanes", 17 June 1813; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Collin de Sussy, Jean-Baptiste, to "the Directeur général des Douanes", 14 Febr. 1814; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Commissaires de la Comptabilité, to Regardin, 16 Jan. 1793; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Constant de Rebecque, Benjamin, to Bossange, Libraire, May [1824?]; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Cornu, to ?, 12 Sept. 1797; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Cornudet, Senateur, to the Secrétaire Général du Ministere des Finances, n.d. [1803]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Coussaud, J., to the Payeur Général, 1800; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Couthon, Georges, to the Minister of War, 25 August 1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 27)
      ALS in French, plus translation. Couthon recommends the Citizen Pepin, "one of the four brave patriots who denounced the evil-doers [malveillants] of [his] batallion" to the attention of the Minister.
    - Couthon, Georges, to the Commission Générale des Monnaies, 4 January 1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 28)
      ALS in French. Recommends the Citizen Faucheur.
    - Craon, Princess of Beauvau-, to Jean-Henri Nederman (Music Instrument Maker and Publisher), 1793?; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 29a)
    - Emmanuel Cretet, Conseiller d'Etat*, 17 July 1805; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 29b)
      ALS in French: note about "la Caisse d'amortissement"
    - Custine, Adam Philippe de, 10 June 1772; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 30)
      ALS in French [certificate, with a significant seal of the Régiment de Rouergue], plus translation, and a portrait of Custine.
    - Custine, Adam Philippe de, to Rochambeau, n.d. (circa 1780); 4 leaves (Box 3, Folder 31)
      ALS in French titled "Etats des objets à traiter au conseil d'Administration", containing a long list of supplies, clothing, weapons and equipment, with their estimated cost, for the Régiment de Saintonge, which was selected in 1780 by the Count de Rochambeau to participate in the French expeditionary force to America.
    - Cuvier, Baron Georges, to Mr. Dubernard de la Villette, Pierre, 31 August, 1820; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Diplôme de Bachelier ès-lettres, plus a portrait of Cuvier
    - Dabadie, Jean Melchior, to Reverony, 2 April 1802; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Daendels, General Herman, to General Van Dam[me], 15 Nov. 1794; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Dalberg, Emmerich, to Mr. Bréguet, March 1828; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Dampierre, Marquis de, to the Minister of War, March 1793; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Dampierre, Marquis de, to General Dumouriez, 20 August 1792; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves + 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 37)
      ALS in French, plus translation, plus portraits and notes
    - Dampierre, Marquis de, to ?, 21 Febr. 1788; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Danton, Georges, n.d. [1792]; 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Signature, plus portraits of Danton
    - Daru, Pierre Antoine, to General Canelaux, 1 Nov. 1794; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Daru, Comte Pierre Antoine, to Joseph Defermon, 30 August 1808; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 3, Folder 41a)
      ALS in French [endorsed by Defermon], plus a portrait of Daru and biographical notes on Defermon
    - Daru, Pierre Antoine, to Roger, conseiller de l'Université Impériale*, 27 August 1812; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 41b)
    - Dauberval, to the Administrateurs de la Gironde, 15 Sept. 1797; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Dauphiné, Représentants des Trois Ordres de la Province de, to King Louis XVI., [22 July 1788]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 43)
      Document in French, copy
    - Daure, Jean, 23 Sept. 1799; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - David, Jacques Louis, to ?, 14 Oct 1776; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 45)
      ALS in French [authentic?]
    - David, Mme Jacques Louis, to Lemercier, n.d. [early 1800s]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 46)
      ALS in French, plus sealed envelop, plus translation
    - Davout, Louis, to Berthier, August 1804; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 47a)
    - Davout, Louis, to his mother*, February 1809; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 47b)
      ALS in French: "Ma femme n'a jamais douté que vous ne lui rendiez justice, vous êtes trop attachée au bonheur de votre fils ainé..." signed "le maréchal duc d'Auerstaedt"
    - Davout, Louis, to Clarke, duc de Feltre*, 16 may 1811; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 47c)
      ALS in French: placement of officers
    - Debelle, General, to ?, n.d. [1800]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Debry, Jean Antoine, to Charles ?, n.d.; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 49)
      ALS in French, plus note
    - Decazes, Elie, to the Minister of Finance, 17 October 1817; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Decrès, Denis, to Napoleon I, 17 May 1808; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Decrès, Denis, to the Minister of Finance*, 6 April 1802; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 52a)
      ALS in French concerning the maritime trade between France and England, and esp. English smugglers. "Le rétablissement de la paix entre la France et la Grande-Bretagne exige une réciprocité d'égards et de bons procédés dont c'est en quelque sorte s'écarter que d'exciter les sujets de cette puissance a des spéculations frauduleuses et prohibées par ses loix... il serait dangereux que le Gouvernement britannique fût informé de la faveur que la République acorde aux fraudeurs anglais. "
    - Decrès, Denis, to the Préfet of Finistère, 9 December 1802; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 3, Folder 52b)
      ALS in French, plus a portrait and biographical notes
    - Decrès, Denis, to the mathematician and astronomer Delambre*, 23 April 1804; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 52c)
      ALS in French about aerostatic balloons
    - Defermon, to the Minister of Finance, 14 June 1800; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Dejean, Directeur de l'Administration de la Guerre, to Louis Bonaparte, 20 Sept. 1803; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 54a)
    - Dejean, Directeur de l'Administration de la Guerre, to Louis Bonaparte, 20 Sept. 1803; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 54a)
    - Dejean, Directeur de l'Administration de la Guerre*, 29 March 1807; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 54b)
      ALS in French about General Philibert Fressinet "[qui] a tenu dans plusieurs sociétés des propos plus qu'indiscrets et sur l'état de la Grande Armée en Pologne et sur les projets de l'Empereur." Fressinet was declared persona non grata and banned from Paris « pour des propos faits dans un lieu public mais qu’il nia avec beaucoup de constance » (28 avril 1807).
    - Dejean, Grand-Trésorier de la Légion d'honneur, to the writer Jacques-Henri Bernardin de Saint-Pierre*, 30 April 1808; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 54c)
      ALS in French about the schooling of Virginie de Saint-Pierre at the Maison de la Légion d'honneur
    - Delaborde, General Henri, to General Lecourbe, 31 Oct. 1799; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 55)
      ALS in French, plus translation, and a note
    - Delacroix, Charles, to the Citoyen Rocquesante, 1795; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Delacroix, Charles, 1794-1809; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 57)
      4 ALS in French
    - Delaunay [topographer], to the Commission des Travaux Publics, 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Delessart [?], to the Administrators of the Dpt. of Finistere, 9 Jan. 1792; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Delessert, Gabriel, to Mr. Galignani, n.d. [1857?]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Deleneufcour, Pierre, to the Minister of Police, 1799; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 61)
      ALS in French, plus a biographical note
  - Dem-E (Box 4)
    - Dembarrere, Jean, to Lemercier, 20 Aug. 1809; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 4, Folder 1)
      ALS in French, plus translation, and notes
    - General Demont, to his Sister, 1794; 1 leaf + 3 leaves + 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 2)
      ALS in French, plus full translation, and biographical note
    - Denon, Vivant, to a Lady, n.d.; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 3)
      ALS in French, plus two portraits of Denon
    - General Desaix, to Barras, 18 May 1798; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 7 leaves (Box 4, Folder 4)
      ALS in French, plus translation, and portraits of Desaix
    - General Desaix, to ?, n.d.; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Desgenettes, Nicolas, to savary, Duc de Rovigo, 27 Dec. 1810; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 6)
      ALS in French, plus portraits of Desgenettes
    - General Dessole to General Lecourbe, 1 May 1800; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Dillon, Arthur, to mr. Gorsy, 5 Oct. 1792; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Dillon, Arthur, to Duportail, 18 June 1791; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Doubs, Department of the, 25 Jan. 1795; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Drouet d'Erlon, Jean Baptiste, to the Minister of War, 10 Nov. 1814; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Drouet de Santerre, Marie, to her Daughter, June 1847; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Drouhard, Lieutenant, to the National Convention, 1794; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Drouot, general, to Mr. Hersant, 20 Aug. 1809; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 4, Folder 14)
      ALS in French, plus translation, and notes. Documents the Bonapartist emigration in the USA after 1815.
    - Dubail, Priest, to [the Republican Authorities], 1800?; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Dubois, Louis Nicolas [Préfet de Police de Paris], 16 Aug. 1802; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Passport delivered to Mr. Laborde, allowing him to travel to St. Domingue
    - Dubois, Dieudonné [Préfet de la Gironde], to Legrand [Administration des Finances], 1803; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Dubois-Crancé, to the Administrators of Finistère, 3 Oct. 1799; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Dubois-Crancé, to the Administrators of Loire-Inférieure, 9 March 1794; 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 4, Folder 19)
      ALS in French, plus portraits and notes
    - Du Bois du Bais, Louis, 2 Sept. 1793; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 20)
      ALS in French, plus translation, and note
    - Dubreton, Commissaire Ordonnateur de la 1ere Division militaire, to Mr. Bainville, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Duchâtel, Charles, to the Minister of Finance, 24 May 1800; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Duchâtel, Charles, to the Minister of Finance, 26 Sept. 1800; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Duchâtel and Rennesson, 10 Dec. 1795; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Duclaux, Adjudant Major de la Place de Milan (Italy), to Perillier, 1796; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Dugommier, Jacques-Coquille, to Ajudant-General Miquel, 22 Sept. 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf +1 leaf (4.26 bis) (Box 4, Folder 26)
      ALS in French with translation, plus another ALS
    - Dugua, General, to the Intendant Général de l'Armée d'Egypte, 13 Nov. 1799; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 27)
      [Cairo, Egypt] ALS in French and Arabic
    - Duhesme, General, to General Marmont, 27 April 1807; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 28)
      [Padova, Italy] ALS in French
    - Duhesme, General, to the Préfet du Rhône, 12ay 1802; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Dulaure, Jacques, tio Baron Cuvillers, 7 Oct. 1824; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Dumas, Alexandre, to the Gazette Musicale de Paris, 20 May 1840; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 31)
      ALS in French annotated byAlexandre Dumas Fils, plus translation and portraits of Dumas père
    - Dumas, Matthieu (Conseiller d'Etat), to Mr. Villemanzy, 17 Sept. 1810; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Dumouriez, General, n.d.; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Dumouriez, Charles, 1782; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Dupin, Préfet des Deux-Sèvres, 1. March 1809; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 35a)
      Certificate in French, plus a portrait and notes
    - Duplaine, teacher of French in Philadelphia, to the French consul in Charleston*, 15 May 1794; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 35b)
      ALS in French, plus a translation: about French expatriates suspected of false patriotism, and about the hostile embargo decided by the US Congress against Great-Britain on March 1794.
    - Duplaine, teacher of French in Philadelphia, to the French consul in Charleston*, 1 June 1794; 4 leaves (Box 4, Folder 35b)
      ALS in French (with translation) reflecting the plots of rival French factions in America, and mentioning the lifting of the American embargo; the activities of “Citizen Genêt” who issued privateering commissions that authorized the bearers, regardless of their country of origin, to seize British merchant ships and their cargo for personal profit, with the approval and protection of the French Government, and then even allowed the so-called Little Democrat to sail and begin attacking British shipping, in direct violation of US neutrality.
    - Duplaine, teacher of French in Philadelphia, to the French consul in Charleston*, 12 June 1794; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 35c)
      ALS in French (with translation)about the attempts made by a French diplomat, Fauchet, to obtain a million dollars instalment payment of the debt from the US: "His request was granted in the House [but] refused in the Senate... A bit more knowledge of the country would have saved him from this unpleasantness." Also, about the fact that Moissonnier, the French consul in Baltimore, is going to be replaced.
    - Dupont, Cour des Compte, to ?, 26 April 1813; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Duportail, Louis, to the Regimental Officers in Charge of the Supplies, 1st October 1791; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Duquesnoy, Ernest, 7 Jan. 1794; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 38)
      ALS in French, endorsed by Joseph Lebon, plus translation
    - Durand-Maillane, Pierre Toussaint, to the Administrators of the Var, 15 Sept. 1793; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Duroc, General [in his capacity as Gouverneur du Palais Impérial], 1804, 1811; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 5 leaves (Box 4, Folder 40)
      ALS in French, plus a second letter, plus portraits and notes
    - Durutte, General, to ?, 1806; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 4, Folder 41)
      ALS in French, plus portrait and notes
    - Duval, Capitaine, and Chauvot, Chirurgien, 31 Oct. 1793; 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - École de Mars, [June /October] 1794; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 43)
      ALS in French, signed by Billaut-Varenne, Prieur, and Barère, members of the Comité de Salut Public, about the hospital of the school
    - Estaing, Admiral d', 4 May 1790; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 44)
      ALS in French; confirms that le Chevalier de Bellefond fought bravely at Savannah in 1779
    - Ezz, Member of the Administrative Chamber of Zurich [Switzerland], to General Montchoisi, 1799; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Fa-France, Convention Nationale (Box 5)
    - Fabre [de l'Aude], Comte, to the Minister of Finance, 19 Sept. 1808; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Fain, Agathon, to ?, [between 1809 / 1814]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Faipoult, Préfet de l'Escaut, to the Administration of Finance, 16 Nov. 1802; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Fauvre-Labrunerie, Charles, to De Pille, 7 Nov. 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Faviers, Matthieu, Commissaire-Ordonnateur en Chef de l'Armée, to ?, 7 Dec. 1799; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 5)
      [Zurich] ALS in French
    - Férino, general, to the Directeur de la Guerre, 19 June 1802; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Ferroux, Etienne Joseph, to Defermon and Obelin, 5 Jan. 1798; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Fernig, Theophile, to his cousin Andeval, 7 Jan. 1798; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Fesh, Cardinal, to the Préfet de Seine et Oise, 28 Febr. 1809; 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Fezensac, Duc de (Montesquiou-), to Mr. Dubrusle, n.d. [after 1852]; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Flesselles, Jacques de, to the Administrators of la Fabrique de Lyon, 1. May 1769; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Fleuriot-Lescot, to the Agence des Domaines Nationauix du District de Paris, 16 July 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Fontanes, Louis de, to Mr. Reynouard, 30 Sept. 1816; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 5, Folder 13)
      ALS in French, plus translation, a portrait of Fontanes, and notes. Fontanes congratulates Reynouard on his "Grammaire de la Langue romane": "Vingt doctes Bénédictins se feraient honneur de vos recherches."
    - Fontanes, Louis de, to General Count Dumas, c. 1810; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 14)
      ALS in French: contains some of Fontanes's views about higher education (Ecole normale superieure, nonsense of creating a chair of poetry at the Collège de France, Delille), as well as an eulogy of Napoleon.
    - Forfait, Pierre Alexandre, to the Concierge de la Maison d'Arrêt de [Sainte-]Pélagie, 15 July 1805; 1 leaf + 4 leaves (Box 5, Folder 15)
      ALS in French, plus another letter [to ?, 1805] notes
    - Forfait, Pierre Alexandre, to the Minister of Finance, 15 Nov. 1800; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Fossa, Comte, to ?, 21 April 1809; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Fouché, Joseph, 1794; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 18)
      ALS in French, plus translation. This is an endorsement by Fouché of a petition by Manufacturer Fauchet of Saint-Etienne, for iron and steel
    - Fouché, Joseph, to Pourtalet [?], Négociant [Purchasing Agent], 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 3 leaves (Box 5, Folder 19)
      ALS in French, plus a second letter also sent from "Commune Affranchie" [= Lyon], a portrait of Fouché, and notes. "La République a l'oeil ouvert sur tous ses agents. Malheur à ceux qui la trompent ou qui la trahissent."
    - Fouché, Joseph, to General Girardon, 1802; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Foulon, Joseph. to M. de Villehelio, 1779; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Fouquier-Tinville, Antoine, 31 May 1794; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 5, Folder 22)
      ALS in French, plus translation, a portrait, and a notice. Release from jail (Pierre-Claude Seulfort, colporteur.)
    - Fourcroy, Antoine, to Mr. Chassiron, 4 March 1805; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Foy, General Maximilien, to General Dorseneo, 25 June 1798; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 2 leaves (Box 5, Folder 24)
      ALS in French, plus translation and portraits
    - France. Administration municipale de Lille, to Villard, 1796; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - France. Aide de camp du général Clarke au général Quantin, 1796; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - France. Ambassadeur de la République Française près la République Cisalpine, 28 March 1799; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 27)
      [Milano] ALS in French
    - France. Ambassadeur de la République Française près la République Cisalpine, 21 April 1799; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 28)